Guide to the Paul Rapelye Papers, 1820-1823
Paul Rapelye papers 1820-1823
Rapelye, Paul, fl. 1820-1823
1.5 Linear Feet 14 Items
Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The papers of Paul Rapelye, commission merchant from Charleston, South Carolina, were purchased by the Rubenstein Library in 1979 and 1983.
Biographical Note
In October 1821, Paul Rapelye, a commission merchant, was a partner in the firm of Wm. S. Bennett and Co., of Charleston, S.C. During 1820-1823, however, he also operated variously in the firms of P. Rapelye and Co. in Savannah and Paul Rapelye in Savannah, New York City, and Manchester, England.
Collection Overview
The papers of Paul Rapelye span the years 1820-1823. They consist of eight account books, 1820-1823, one letter book, 1821-1823, and five letters, 1820-1822, that mostly concern mercantile trade. He and his associates traded primarily in cloth, cloth goods, and clothing, but also occasionally in rice, cotton, and other commodities. Rapelye traveled and conducted business in Charleston, Savannah, New York city, and Manchester, England.
In a letter of July 15, 1822, auctioneer Jacob Rapelye of Charleston discussed his business and the aborted slave insurrection led by Denmark Vesey. There is also a reference to the capture of a Portuguese slave ship and the disposition of the slaves (1820, July 27).
The collection is divided into correspondence and account books, the latter arranged under the names of the companies to which they belonged.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Wm. S. Bennett and Co. (Charleston, S.C.)
Commission merchants
Clothing trade
Textile fabrics
Slavery -- Insurrections, etc.--South Carolina
Rice trade -- South Carolina
Cotton trade -- South Carolina
Auctioneers -- South Carolina
Charleston (S.C.) -- Commerce
Savannah (Ga.) -- Commerce
New York (N.Y.) -- Commerce
Manchester (England) -- Commerce
Slave-trade
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence, 1820-1822
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
- Volumes
  - P. Rapelye and Co.: Inventory, 1820 (Box 1)
  - Paul Rapelye:
    - Invoice Book, 1820-1821
    - Invoice Book, 1822-1823
    - Ledger, 1820 -1821 (Box 2)
    - Index to Ledger, 1820-1821
    - Daybook, 1820-1821
  - Wm. S. Bennett and Co.:
    - Letter Book, 1821-1823 (Box 3)
    - Sales at Auction, 1821-1822
    - Sales at Auction, 1822